The science and practice of enhancing
human performance for sport, play, and
life. Welcome to
perform. I'm Dr. Andy Galpin. I'm a
professor and scientist and the
executive director of the human
performance center at Parker University.
And today I'm speaking with Dr. Allison
Bger. Allison is a neuroscientist who
has spent most of her career focusing on
sleep and specifically sleep resilience
which is one way of thinking about how
do we become more efficient and
effective with sleep regardless of the
situation. classic examples of that. Her
research has looked at everything from
athletes traveling from one coast to the
other coast, military individuals sleep
on Antarctica and in space, as well as
just a ton of research for regular
people. And how do we just become the
most effective we can? What effective
sleep is is actually something I learned
a lot about today and something that you
will pick up on as Allison shared. what
that actually means, how do you
determine it, how you can actually
become more specific and precise to your
individual sleep needs, and overall how
to better think about sleep for not only
surviving, but thriving. Allison is a
fantastic scientist. Her publications
are numerous, but she spent so much time
in the field dealing with individuals
that I think the true value you're going
to get out of this episode is
understanding how that information that
she has gleaned from her research
actually manifests itself in the
practical real world scenario. And so I
learned a ton. I know you're going to
learn a ton about becoming a resilient
and highly effective sleeper. So with
that all said, I hope you enjoyed
today's episode with Dr. Allison Bger.
Dr. Allison Brager, thank you so much
for coming out. There's a lot of cool
stuff I want to get into today. I I was
hoping we could start off actually with
dispelling a huge sleep myth. Mhm. I'm
from the West Coast. You're from the
Midwest. As you are well aware, there is
a huge East Coast bias for sports teams.
We all know that the West Coast gets no
love. We get unfair placements and and
things. Um, can you please confirm and
share with the rest of the world that
there is in fact a huge advantage for
East Coast teams that it is easier, that
they win more, that everything is better
and and and the West Coast teams are
truly at a disadvantage? It's actually
the opposite. No,
no, during the regular season, it's
actually the opposite. So, what's that?
That's the classic NFL study that was
done by some famous uh Stanford sleep
physicians in the '9s that we sort of
reconfirmed uh in the late 2000s. Uh but
this idea that West Coast teams, at
least during the regular season, are
playing games that are more attuned to
their circadian peak than their
circadian trail. So basically what that
means is uh if you just control for
biological time they're playing games
more in their midm morning um or early
evening and so that's what gives them
this advantage uh in terms of
performance which has been correlated
with injury risk. So, they're five times
less likely, especially if you look at
like defensive linemen, offensive
linemen, um, to less likely to get
injured compared to the New England
Patriots and the Philadelphia Eagles and
all the above. So, I'm sorry. I can't
help you with this. All lies. I refuse
to believe your data. This, you're
clearly bought by big East Coast sports.
I get it. I don't trust it. I I'm
actually a huge San Francisco 49ers fan
myself. Even worse. Even worse, get out.
I uh I coach Fred Warner. He's a good
friend of mine, but outside and I tell
him he he knows this. He knows I hope he
loses every game of the year, but that
he wins the MVP. I just like I'm open
with my rooting on that one. In terms of
the injuries, actually, this is sort of
interesting. Is there a particular type
of injury? Is it brain injuries or soft
tissue or hamstrings or did it sort of
just be across the board
with something like that? That was a
great question. And so we more or less
just looked at um number of weeks spent
on injury reserve. Yeah. Uh that was the
only available to us at the time. Um but
we actually were able recently to get
some of the concussion data uh because
that was something that came out of the
NFL lawsuit is they had to start
publicly recording when players had
gotten concussed um during a game and
stuff. So we're my uh no pressure to my
wife. She's trying to help me with those
types of analyses now. She's much better
at statistics than I am. Well, I hope
she doesn't screw it and I hope she's
not bought by big East Coast like like
you are. We get some real data out of
this. Um, she's a Miami Dolphins fan, so
I don't know. She can have it. She can
No, no one's scared of the Dolphins. Uh,
why why does it actually matter? How
much of a winning advantage is it? What
like what are we talking about? And any
insights into We don't have to
necessarily go into like deep molecular
mechanism, but you're welcome to. Sure.
But like why in the world would someone
playing a few hours outside of their
optimal range actually matter? How does
that transfer I guess into winning a
game? That's a big leap from small thing
to winning a football game, right? I
mean that's a great question because
these are correlative. They're not
causitive relationships. Um but it does
speak to the robustness of the circadian
clock, right? So, in general, uh,
regardless of if you're a morning
person, an evening person, for the most
part, the circadian clock and the daily
rhythms of endocrine function, behavior,
um, and all the physiological processes
associated with the circadian clock um,
are predictable. And a lot of these
performance attributes have to do with
rising levels of cortisol in the
morning. Right? When we upon awakening,
that's when cortisol begins to rise and
the circadian clock begins to reach peak
levels of alertness. And then peak
levels of alertness are reached roughly
around 11:00 a.m. to 1:00 p.m. depending
on who you are. Um, and so if you are
training, if you are competing during
that time, um, you're capitalizing on
that peak of cortisol, which is
obviously going to mobilize energy
reserves. um and contribute to those
aspects of attention, vigilance, focus
um and all the above. So, it's probably
a combination of every physiological
factor, physical performance, recovery,
cognitive, that's all combining. Um and
I appreciate you saying that just
correlation, but those correlations have
been shown in the NBA, the NHL, Major
League Baseball. I think it's pretty
well established at this point that that
is a a real phenomenon. Yeah. I I mean I
also think too, right, there's a huge
genetic component and that's a lot of
what I've studied my whole life is the
genetics of sleep physiology and
circadian physiology is I do believe
people select for their sport based on
if they're a morning person or evening
person. Like I grew up a gymnast. Uh we
always practice at night. We didn't
necessarily compete at night. Uh but I
was always coming home from gymnastics
practice at 9:00 p.m. doing my homework,
going to bed. My parents are both night
owls. Um, so and I know I, you know, did
the 23 and me raw data analysis. I'm a
night owl. Uh, but I I bet it's like
that with other sports as well, like
right boxing, MMA, probably pre-select
for night owls. Um, same with uh NBA uh
and NHL players, you know, how much of a
an effect does it have if you are
mismatched?
So there actually is data to show that
there is a significant effect. Um there
was a study that came out I can't
remember how many years ago but it was
in current biology and they were looking
at rugby players um and they were
looking at it in relation to chronotype
and they essentially found that if you
had greater interindividual variability
in chronotype on a team you were more
likely those to win rugby matches
because you weren't a sensitive I get
it. Yeah. Yeah. because you're not just
playing games at night like an NBA or an
NHL team. You're playing games either in
the morning, the afternoon, or the
evening. Now, I imagine it would
probably be the opposite for NBA or an
NHL teams. I don't know if anyone's
actually done this analysis. You
probably want less interindividual
variability in chronoype and you want to
pre-seelelect for more evening types.
So, we got to start genetically
screening people for our draft process.
I mean, you know, Gatka is one of my
favorite movies. I'm not going to say
it's like the be all end all, but uh
every you know, I try to every student
that I I teach, I always try to expose
them to, uh, you know, that movie for
that reason. Yeah, it's super
interesting. When it comes to
chronotype, there's clearly, as you
talked about, there are some known
genetic components to that. I've always
been interested though of how much of
that do we know at this point? We may
not know much regarding habituation
throughout life, right? So if your
parents were night owls, do you simply
become a night owl because of genetic
components or because you just simply
got brought up in a culture that was
like that, language that was like that,
you know, your parents say, "Oh, I'm
just a night person." Things like that.
Yeah. Do we have any insights into like
how much play is genetically
predetermined versus systemally grown
into the person's behavior? I don't know
of any data that exists, but I mean I
could say that would make sense, right?
Because if you're used to being in a
household who eats dinner extremely
late, I mean my parents are Eastern
Europeans, so like we never do anything
on time or early, right? So like dinner
was around 8:39 and guess what? I'm
still an 8:30, 9 p.m. eater. Like I go
to the gym and then I eat really late,
but I also go to bed really late and
then sleep in and, you know, wake up
late, too. Um, and whether or not that's
nature versus nurture. Yeah. I mean, I'm
we do know, at least from adult sleep
habits, for example, that um the sleep
habits that are instilled in you as a
child, whether good, bad, or ugly, do
carry on with you into college. And then
when you are an adult and able to make
your full decision. So um a lot of um
behavioral sleep physicians will will
tell you that that like that's why it's
so important for parents to establish
bedtime routines and be the examples of
good hygiene for their children because
that will have a lasting impression when
those kids do become of age and can make
their own decisions.
Today's episode is sponsored by AG1. AG1
is a vitamin mineral drink with
probiotics, prebiotics, and adaptogens.
Initially, I was extremely skeptical of
AG1, as I am with all supplement
companies. But after months of
discussions with their lead nutritional
scientist and the general team at AG1,
I've been impressed by AG1's commitment
to sourcing the highest quality
ingredients and constantly updating
their formulas to have the right
ingredients in the optimal amounts. By
now, it is abundantly clear that the gut
microbiome plays a critical role in
everything from body composition to bone
health to mental health. And the
probiotics and prebiotics in AG1 help to
promote a healthy gut microbiome,
improve digestion, reduce food cravings,
and increase short- chain fatty acids,
which play a critical role in regulating
metabolism and immune responses. It's
for these reasons and many others that I
personally take AG1 almost every day.
Now, it's of course not a replacement
for eating whole healthy foods, but it
is a great way to make sure that you're
plugging in any gaps in your nutrition
to improve your energy, bolster your
immune system, and just generally help
promote a healthy gut microbiome and
more. If you'd like to try AG1, you can
go to
drinkagg.com/perform to receive five
free travel packs, plus a year supply of
vitamin D3 plus K2. Again, that's
drinkagg.com/perform to receive five
free travel packs, plus a year supply of
vitamin D3 plus K2. Today's episode is
also sponsored by EightLe. Eight makes
smart mattress covers with cooling,
heating, sleep tracking, and more. I've
personally been sleeping on an EightLe
mattress cover for years now, and it's
absolutely glorious. I love it so much
that I hate traveling away from home
because it means I can't sleep on my
Eight Sleep Pod 4 Ultra. As you'll hear
me talk about endlessly on this podcast,
there really is nothing you can do that
makes more of an impact on your health
and performance than getting tremendous
sleep. And getting great sleep requires
having your body temperature drop a
couple of degrees at night. And that's
hard to do on your own. The eight sleep
has been a gamecher for me because I run
hot at night or as my wife calls it, I'm
a furnace. If I don't have something
like an eight sleep helping me cool
down, I'll wake up in the middle of the
night overheating and not feeling great.
This is something I've also found in
many of the people that I coach,
especially those who are really
physically active. The eightle pod 4
Ultra has two times more cooling power
yet is virtually silent and it has
highfidelity sleep tracking and even has
snoring detection that'll automatically
lift your head a few degrees to improve
air flow and stop your snoring. If you'd
like to try eight, go to eight at
eight.com/perform to save $350 off your
Pod 4 Ultra. Asleep currently ships to
the US, Canada, the UK, select countries
in the EU and even Australia. Again,
that's
eight.com/perform. Do we have any
insights on how changeable chronotype
is? Right. So if you say got a job and
they said Alisonson like you have to be
into work at 7:00 and whatever the case
is and you had to change that how long
would it take you to shift in a position
where you didn't feel horrible getting
up at 5:00 a.m. versus 8 a.m. or
wherever it went over time you normally
are you like a midnight to 8 sort of
person I am. Yep. My preferred is 11:30
wake up between 7:30 and 8. So if that
got shifted by two or three hours, um I
guess two-part question, can you
actually change your chronoype? And then
obviously you can adjust that time
independent of changing chronoype. So
the second question then is how long
would it take you to truly I mean it
probably take you a few days or a week
to where you're like not waking up
feeling terrible, but you would not be
optimized would be my assumption. How
long would that take? So I come from the
camp of researchers, you know, nature
over nurture. Um, and I I'll use
uh pre-clinical animal models as an
example. Um, we have engineered
transgenic mice to be extreme early
morning owls or extreme early morning
larks um or extreme night owls um all
through manipulation of the circadian
molecular clock. Um and you can present
them with different stimuli in the
environment. You know, in the circadian
world, we call them zeite gabers. So,
you can present them with repeatable,
predictable photoic information or
non-photic information such as food,
some type of rewarding stimulus,
exercise, social stimulation, etc. But
as soon as you remove that
predictability of that zeitgeab or time
cue, then the organism will revert back
to its genetic natural rhythm. Um, and I
think the same is true in humans. I use,
you know, again, anecdotal evidence. Um,
but being in the military, at one point,
I was a company commander, uh, in a
leadership position. And, um, in order
to establish rapport and camaraderie
with my brigade commander, he is an
extreme morning person, and he works out
at 5:00 a.m. So, what that meant is I
had to wake up every day at 4:00 a.m. to
then get to the gym to work out with him
at 5:00 am. Again, it wasn't mandatory,
but I knew it's, you know, just part of
the process of being his subordinate.
Um, and during that time, I would find
myself if I didn't go to bed exactly at
8:00 p.m., if I didn't keep all those
other non-photic things in my life
stable, such as when I ate, uh, how much
I was hydrating throughout the day,
etc., Like I got sick pretty often
because my body just biologically fights
against being a morning person. So in
that particular case again, you were
able to get through it, but you were not
thriving. Exact. Oh, I was not thriving.
I wasn't even optimizing. I was just
trying to stabilize surviving. Survive.
Exactly. Through the day. Exactly. I
mean that's why I tell people like at
the end of the day I will never be
anyone important ever in the military
even if I wanted to because I am a night
person and things such as the military
pre-select for morning people and I am
not that person and I will never be one
of the issues with those
historical organizations right academia
is its own little thing right that's why
I thrived actually in academia right
land night owls. Yeah, I'm the opposite.
Like I'm a morning person big time and I
would hate I'd hate the 11 p.m.
meetings. I hate just all that stuff,
right? I'm like, but I'm actually
wondering if we've done ourselves quite
the disservice in those organizations of
of saying no like I mean obviously we're
hopefully we're past the point where
waking up early is a badge of honor and
do those things. But is that actually
that is that culture still pretty true
in the military? I would say it's pretty
true. I think people who are night owls
are considered to be lazy. Yeah, I still
I I know I get judged for being a night
owl in the military. But you hold your
ground pretty good, right? I do. Well, I
mean I it's mine's supported by science,
you know. I take no prisoners. I'm not
going to I don't care what other people
think, you know. So, you're going to
you're going to roll in four hours after
everybody else, but you'll stay there
four hours later. Exactly. Exactly. And
get your stuff done. Yep. Yep. Going
back to your your mouse studies, uh we
were laughing earlier this morning about
uh how you got a little bit of a a shout
out during the uh State of the Union.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Um maybe it' be
easier. Would you mind sharing a little
bit about what I'm talking about because
it's quite funny. Yeah. So um one of the
transgenic mouse models I worked on um
as a posttock at Morehouse School of
Medicine was the four core genotype
mouse line. was a mouse line created by
Art Arnold out here actually in UCLA.
Um, and what it is is it's a divergence
of chromosonal sex with hormonal sex.
And the purpose of developing this mouse
line is it presents a unique way to look
at the influence of chromosomes, so sex
chromosomes versus hormonal release of
testosterone and estrogen on just
physiology and behavior. So it actually
worked out to be an elegant mouse model.
It's very elegant. Exactly. To look at
sex differences in sleep. Uh so to
understand how sleep pressure builds
differently amongst biological males
versus biological females. Um and you
know bottom line of doing using the
sophisticated mouse model is we know
that a lot of sleep traits um are due to
this it's called the SRY gene. So the
testes determining gene um that is
responsible for diff sex differences in
the accumulation of sleep pressure
across the waking day and then the
presentation of daytime sleepiness. Uh
so bottom line being that biological
males are more prone to daytime
sleepiness. Um whereas females are not
and then biological females although
they have greater difficulties entering
sleep itself at night uh the quality and
the efficiency of their sleep is greater
than males. How could you have answered
that question without that model? I mean
we were only answering the hormonal
piece of it really. So how would you do
without it? So my postoc mentor that was
his I guess landmark study as a postoc
at Northwestern with Dr. Fred Turk. Uh
so Dr. Dr. Kimma Paul that's who I
worked with as a postoc he essentially
would um remove the gonads of these
adult mice right so stopping circulation
of estrogen and
testosterone but you couldn't see these
nuance differences and like that's why
you needed the chromosonal sex and the
genetic manipulation piece um of it and
it's important to realize that like
biological sex differences are really
complicated it's not just hormonal sex
it is also
chromosonal sex that seems to play the
greatest role on physiology and
behavior. I actually want to go back to
some of those findings, right, about
sleep pressure and and sex differences.
But the reason this came up, I guess, in
that speech was this was one of the
examples of wasteful spending. Is that a
fair way that it was characterized?
Correct. Yes. And uh and you and I and
I'm sure many people on your team had a
good laugh at that, right? Like it's
really unfortunate and we're not going
to spend too much time here, but it's
very unfortunate that uh a title of a
paper, a title of a study section can
get cut when really there is tremendous
value for all of us behind that with
very little attention paid to who's
doing it, what's happening and category
is.
I mean, you know, so social
political norms aside, like men and
women are different and like these
animal models exist to understand
biologically why men are and women are
different. And then when it comes to
treating things such as sleep disorders
or managing sleep disturbances, which
you know 70% of the world, if not more,
suffer from. That's how you target and
to address them is through the lens of
biology. But I mean that's just my own
humble opinion and now and now you can't
even study it. Yeah. Because great.
Okay. Um let's get back to some of those
findings. That was an animal model. How
do we know anything about how much that
or how little that is actually going to
transfer over into human models? Do we
have any data on sleep pressure, sleep
inertia, some of those other things you
brought up that look like they're
different based on chromosomes alone?
What do we know about the uh impact on
humans? So, honestly, I haven't really
seen much in the literature.
Um I mean, I'm sure you can look at like
single nucleotide polymorphisms
um in the SR gene for example. But
honestly, I don't know if anyone has
investigated that per se. Um I mean I
guess you can look at
um like interex individuals in
individuals. So someone who has like for
example androgen uh deficiency syndrome
something like that. Um but I don't
think that's been characterized enough
in in humans. Tough study to pull off. I
will say um so a few months ago, when
was that? It was about a year ago. I
presented at the NSCA conference that's
geared towards tactical populations and
I did this whole deep dive lecture. I'm
sure some people appreciated it, but a
lot of people were like, "Okay, where's
she going with this?" Um, but I was I
started with the four core genotype
model and then I transitioned into uh
the studies we know about women in
sleep. And what's crazy is like all this
work that was done by Dr. for Rachel
Rachel Manber at uh Stanford University
and Dr. Terry Lee um at Yale University
is like it was done in the 80s and it
just stayed in this vault for like 45
years until quite honestly wearable
companies and you know I'll give a shout
out to Whoop like recognized that we
need to focus on like female differences
in sleep. Uh and a lot of people think
that that research is unknown or unheard
of but actually it was done in the 80s.
Yeah. And it was done in a very robust
controlled nature but you know it was
just forgotten for like 45 years. What
do we actually
know about sleep differences between men
and women? And what I actually want to
know about is chromosonally. Yeah. Yeah.
So when you tease out the hormones, how
is it that a a particular whether it's a
polymorphism or some other activity at
the level of uh the genome, how is that
actually manipulating manifesting itself
into sleep? Mhm. Any idea what
mechanisms could possibly there if it's
not endocrine?
So in terms of mechanism of action um we
know that again there's differences in
sleep pressure and if you unpack the
onion uh sleep pressure is manifest from
increasing levels of adenosine
production uh extracellular adenosine
production within the brain particularly
the basil forbrain which is a wake
promoting area. Um so if sleep pressure
is accumulating quickly uh which seems
to be the case uh in biological males by
way of the testes determining gene then
there's more rapid accumulation of
extracellular adenosine and the only way
to pay off that increasing sleep
pressure is through daytime sleep. Yeah.
Um and so with females right it it just
essentially means their rate of
accumulation of sleep pressure uh is
lower which means that the production of
extracellular adenosine would be lower.
Now whether that's been studied, it
hasn't. But like hypothetically just
knowing with all the you know myriad of
studies around accumulating sleep
pressure and extracellular denosine. Um
we predict that's the mechanism of
action. I mean that that's the closest
we can come right at this point right.
Is it fair? Is it a trope? I certainly
know that it feels like the guys that I
know versus the girls that I know you
guys fall asleep fast. Yep. Oh yeah. Is
that actually been demonstrated? Do we
know that? So that's been demonstrated
again in these pre-clinical transgenic
mouse models um using the four core
genotype. It's also been demonstrated in
in human studies. Um so in those studies
that were done in the 80s by Terry Lee
and Rachel Manber, that's exactly what
they found is sleep onset for men is
much quicker. But then when you look at
time to restorative sleep, so that entry
into um stage three non-REM and then REM
sleep, it is uh the latency is quicker
for females. So it might take them
longer to fall asleep, but to get that
restorative sleep, it's much quicker and
then much more efficient across the
night. Do we have any teological or
evolutionary guess as to why that setup
is there? I mean, I think it all goes
back to child rearing, right? Like who's
responsible for children, right? Men are
responsible for propagating children,
but you know women like they are the
caretakers. And I think these are these
built-in neurochemical neuro anatomical
circuits that exist because of you know
relationships between who actually takes
care of the child. How much of it is if
you know psychology versus biology
there? Right. So the the classic thing
you'll hear is like oh women ruminate
more, they think about stuff more.
they're paying attention or is it simply
any host of cascades haven't kicked off
yet? The the pressure isn't high enough.
Do we have any idea what uh I'm I'm sure
it's both are contributing but well I
think that's uh the psychological aspect
from my lens is a part of that
biological
um blueprint right is because females
are going to have greater vigilance and
across the day. Well, what
neurochemically is vigilance? it's
increased acetylcholine release and um
activation of acetylcholine areas of the
brain like the basil forbrain um that
are going to lead to that but again I
see the world in from the lens of nature
versus nurture so I'm not I'm not a very
good uh colleague in in departments of
psychology well you have a degree in
psychology I have an undergraduate
degree in psychology but really it's
neuroscience it's all neuroscience And
so I was fortunate enough that, you
know, I did go to a university that
really um thrived on its neuroscience
curriculum. So, well, nonetheless, I
heard you're a psychologist and what I
just heard you say was uh psychology is
just misunderstood physiology. I get it.
I get it. That's what you said. Dr. Bger
said it. Holding my stamp to that.
Acetylcholine.
Um is that a total concentration issue
that generally is higher or is it a
receptor density or is it both? Do we
have any idea what are actually the sex
differences between acetylcholine?
Um that's a good
question. I mean the studies that I know
exist on sex differences um focus on one
particular area which is the basil
forbrain right that is the the seat of
major acetylolonergic production and
release and activation within the brain.
And then there's like cascading effects
on other areas. Um, but no, I I I
actually think this is the land of great
unknown. I mean, there haven't been a
lot of studies on sex differences and
and physiology and behavior. And if
there were, they were done again in the
80s and 90s. And now, you know, you got
me curious about going back onto PubMed
and Google Scholar and and looking this
up. But yeah, I mean uh the stuff that
has been done since then, a lot of it is
questionnaires. Yeah. Right. It is it's
like pretty low fidelity stuff. Yeah.
Which is good and helpful, but I mean
you need self-report. I mean with our
sleep studies that we do in humans now,
right, we always have an objective
endpoint endocrine or
um even a behavioral cognitive measure,
but it's always paired with self-report.
And sometimes the self-report data is
what lends the more interesting
findings. So women men fall asleep
differently. We get that. What about
total duration and waking up time? Any
sex differences that are notable there?
So I'm happy you asked that because I
feel like there have
been that data has been taken a little
bit too far on social media that men
that excuse me that women need more
sleep than men.
There is a difference in total sleep
time between men and women that was
found again in these studies in
1980s and it's about 25 minutes to 30
minutes different but I come from this
lens is that clinically significant and
that I can't answer that but I feel like
in social media that has been people
have taken that information and a brunt
with it that you know women need to
spend I think I saw something recently
because women take this long to fall
asleep, they need to be in bed for 9 and
a half hours. Uh versus a guy who, you
know, falls asleep quickly. They only
need to be in bed for eight. And I think
at a certain point, like that's just
going to create anxiety around the act
of sleeping that it's going to be more
harmful than helpful. I assume then also
based on this, men nap more than women
do. Yep. Yeah. Yeah. No, we know that
like we know that experimentally. We
know that anecdotally. Um, you know, you
just look at cultures around the world
that have siestas. Uh, and or you know,
it's adopted and celebrated that like
people nap during the day is we know
that men in general cross cultures uh
are more prone to daytime sleepiness. Do
you know if and transgenic mice too? Oh,
you know, name there. Um, are people
napping more or less or the same than we
have historically? That I don't know. I
mean, I feel like at least in the last
years that stigma around napping has
been uh reduced, I would say. I mean, it
still exists in the military. I don't
think it's it's going away. We actually
um my colleagues and I from Walter Reed,
we have a paper that we published in the
um flagship journal of sleep about
around it's called the stigma of
workplace napping. And we strategically
anonymously took quotes from senior
leaders in the military. And I mean we
were flabbergasted. They were like, "No,
if my employees nap, they're lazy. Like
they're not productive." And I'm like,
"You're okay. I just whatever." Yeah, no
comment there. But um yeah, I I feel
like the stigma has been reduced. Um but
I would say I would argue
that earlier in you know generations,
decades earlier that napping was still
more celebrated than it is today. I mean
I know for example, President Eisenhower
or then General Eisenhower used to nap
like in the middle of worldwide conflict
in World War II. He took a nap every
day. Probably very beneficial. Yeah, for
sure. Absolutely. What do we know about
successful versus unsuccessful napping?
In terms of a nap, um, it has to be 30
minutes or less. We do know that with
the exception being a night shift worker
or someone who has chronic insufficient
sleep, right? Um, the recommendation
there is 90 minutes to complete a full
sleep cycle. Um, but historically what
the clinical data has shown is if you
are someone who normally gets sufficient
sleep and you take a nap that is longer
than 30 minutes, then you're more likely
to have issues with sleep onset that
night. Um, or just have issues with
regularity in your your sleep. Um, but
there's also data to show that a 20 to
30 minute nap is sufficient for
immediate improvements in mood, athletic
performance, even cognitive performance.
Do you have any sense of what percentage
of people nap? I don't I would imagine
it's it's fairly low, right? Yeah, I
would I would think it's fairly low
except when you're talking about these
microcosms of cultures, right? like
professional athletes, it seems to be
completely acceptable and celebrated of
of napping. Yeah. Um and I'm sure
there's a few ring leaders like, you
know, I know LeBron James, you were just
talking about that he's a huge proponent
of daytime naps and I I've heard that he
takes multiple naps across the uh the
waking day. But it depends on the
culture, right? I can tell you in my
workplace very very few people nap. you
know, I struggle napping. Like, it just
does not work for me. It doesn't work
for me either. Um, if I have had a
string of nights of insufficient sleep
or if I'm traveling, I will lie down and
like close my eyes for a bit. But I
think it's just a nature of being like a
highly functional ADHD person. I can't
If I happen to fall asleep accidentally
or even on purpose during the day, I'm
going to just feel horrific the whole
rest of the day. I'm going to feel
terrible. Yep. Is that just a good
indication that I just shouldn't do it
or are there ways that I could change
that so I feel feel better when I wake
up or should I just avoid it? So, it's
interesting you say that because um one
of the things that has become more
popular is this idea of a nappuccino or
like having caffeine prior to a nap. Um
and I learned anecdotally that this was
adopted by the trucking industry in the
1970s. And the reason behind it is right
like a cup of coffee or any caffeine
preferably not an energy drink uh before
a nap um it takes about 20 minutes for
the adenosine receptors in your brain to
be impacted. Um so in that 20 minutes
you can take a nap and then wake up
feeling boosted or less groggy um than
you otherwise would without the
caffeine. Um and that has been
experimentally tested in in the lab too.
What circumstances need to happen for
somebody for you to say, "Hey, you
should consider napping, right?" How
does somebody know that they should
think about napping? Is there anything
that you say, "Hey, if AB and C is going
on, you might be a good candidate for
napping or is this something they just
need to go figure out?"
So, I mean, in the populations I work
with, right? Like I work in a world
where most people I'd like to think I'm
a good example, but again, that's also
why I'll never really amount to any, you
know, position. Well, I I think you've
already I think you've already amounted
to plenty of pretty good positions
within the military, but most of which
we can't even talk about. So, yeah,
exactly. Um is um chronic insufficient
sleep, right? If you are not getting
sufficient sleep, so most people between
seven and nine hours a night depending
on who you are, um you need to nap or
you should nap um or engaged in um some
sort of like 20 minute non-activity
throughout the waking day to help offset
that accumulating sleep pressure, right?
because you're already waking up in the
morning with a high level of sleep
pressure uh because you weren't able to
effectively release it at night when you
sleep. While we do recommend in those
populations like hey try to get 20 to 30
minutes, I understand that some people
can't get in that mental head space. But
that's why we have things like
technology now to assist. Um I mean I'll
give a shout out to our dear friends at
Shiftwave. I think that is going to be a
great tool, especially for the tactical
populations I work with, to help them
get into that headsp space of just
turning their brain off, um, and getting
into that meditative deep breath state,
even if it's for like 10 to 15 minutes.
I spend most of my recreational time
paying attention to wildlife. It's a
huge passion of mine. if we can go out
and where I live, blacktail deer and elk
and like that's that's what I spend most
of my passion time on. If you hang
around people that do that, hunters and
um conservationists and outdoors and
biologists and stuff. Yeah. They can
take a three-hour nap in the middle of
the day like nothing, right? Just
nothing. They can go lay down and
they're just gone for hours. Yeah. Every
time I try that, I lay there on the side
of a mountain and it's like rolling
around. There's like zero chance this
happening. I think I know your answer
here, but I would assume that u not a
not a healthy behavior that they have
with sleeping for three hours a day in
the middle of the day. Is is that a fair
characterization of a poor sleep
strategy? So, I'm going to actually
challenge you on that because that's how
human that's how humans used to sleep
before Thomas Edison uh commercialized
electricity. Like so that was like
multifphasic sleep was what through the
course of human evolution used to
practice and honestly if you look at ind
indigenous communities they still
practice that um where they have like
four hours of sleep at night and then
there's four hours of wakefulness and
then they have morning you know sunrise
activity and then they have a 3 four
hour period in the middle of at the
afternoon. Now, it makes sense when you
look at the circadian clock, right?
Because there's two circadian peaks and
two circadian trails throughout the 24-h
hour period. The first dip obviously is
in the middle of the night. Uh that's
when you know core body temperature
driven by the circadian clock is its
lowest between 2 and 4 a.m. But then
there's a second dip in the circadian
alertness signal in the middle of the
afternoon for most people between 2 and
4. And so that's why it is good to push
people towards sleeping or napping
during this time, but and people who,
you know, live off the land and live a
more indigenous lifestyle
um they're just catering to their
natural circadian rhythm uh pre you know
industrialized uh exposure. And do we
think that those people can be perfectly
healthy? Is there any reason to think
that that is actually a problem? No, I
don't think there's an issue at all to
be honest with you. I mean, it's you're
not fighting against human evolution and
biology, right? Because if you look at
most chronic disease states, yeah, in
the country, it's because of fighting
against evolution and biology. And also
too like it goes back to your point of I
think there is evidence um for as
limited as there is between people who
are one chronoype and then tried to be
the other chronotype and looking at
morbidity and mortality. Perfect example
shift workers right people who do night
shift work um have uh an estimate of a
15 years decrease in their lifespan. 15
15 years. So there's a large-scale
epidemiological study that looked at
cancer rates as well as was longitudinal
study of lifespan of night shift workers
um or rotating shift workers and um
their lifespan was reduced by 15 years.
They had significant increases in
cancers across the board. So not just a
particular cancer but all different
types of bodily cancers. Um and then
even the World Health Organization has
labeled shift work as a level two
carcinogen.
Oo, and it it goes back to fighting
against our, you know, evolution and
biology and what our genetic program is.
How do they generally define shift work?
What hours of work? Is it overnight or
is it like swing shift? Like what counts
as shift work? When we say shift work,
we're usually talking about people who
start work at 11:00 p.m. work the
graveyard shift, right? 11 p.m. Get off
7 a.m. Today's episode is sponsored by
Element. Element is an electrolyte drink
mix that has an ideal electrolyte ratio
of sodium, potassium, and magnesium, but
no sugar. Hydration is critical to
performance, both physical and mental
performance. Countless studies have
shown that even a slight degree of
dehydration, even as small as 1%, can
lead to decreases in physical output and
mental performance. We also know that
electrolytes are critical to proper
hydration, which I've been harping on
for years. But you can't do that proper
hydration by only drinking water. You
need to get the right amount of
electrolytes in the right ratios. And
that's why I'm a huge fan of Element. In
fact, many of you will probably remember
that I featured Element in my YouTube
series on optimizing hydration nearly 5
years ago. I featured Element in these
videos because their blend of 1,000
milligs of sodium, 200 milligrams
potassium, and 60 milligrams of
magnesium really is unique and different
than any other electrolyte on the
market, and it has great scientific
support. I use Element constantly,
particularly when I'm sweating a lot,
and I routinely make it a part of my
clients optimization programs. If you'd
like to try Element, you can go to
drinklmntt.com/perform to claim a free
Element sample pack with the purchase of
any Element drink mix. Again, that's
drinklmnt.com/perform to claim a free
sample pack. Today's episode is also
brought to you by Parker University.
Parker is the only university in the
world dedicated exclusively to human
performance, and it's also my new
academic home. I first heard of Parker
after attending their Neurocon seminar
and was stunned. I've been to countless
clinics and conferences and nobody is
even close to Parker seminars. The
speakers, the setup, and the experience
are frankly jaw-dropping. All their
seminars are great, but the upcoming
Miami show, which is June 6th through
8th, is going to be extra special. It's
featuring special guests like my friends
Dr. Gabrielle Lion and fitness expert
Jeff Cavalier and plenty more. But on
top of that, I'm actually hosting a
personal co-seminar that's all about the
practical side of strength training, and
that blends perfectly with the Parker
program. So, imagine going to a
phenomenal lecture on how the nervous
system works, and then popping over and
lifting weights with me personally. All
access tickets are on sale now, but at a
special rate of only
$249, but these will increase as the
dates get closer, so do not wait. And
yes, you heard that right.
$249 gets you full access to the entire
Parker seminar. exhibit hall, nightlife
events, plus a learning and lifting in
the gym with myself and Dan Garner. To
see the exact schedule, full list of
speakers, and get signed up, visit
parkseminars.com. One more time, that's
parkseminars.com. I can't wait to see
you there.
We have dealt I've actually in our um a
number of our companies we've dealt with
a lot of surgeons um emergency medicine
nurses uh
firefighters police and they have to
work at some point there are better and
there are worse policies for that. We've
seen some people where they like 4 days
day shift 4 days night shift right yeah
you can't design a worst possible setup
for those individuals. So if somebody
has to work night shift because we have
to we need it right we need surgeons and
we need physicians and nurses and so
military we win our nation's wars at
night we need people who can operate at
night how do how do you then set them up
for least amount of failure if they have
to work night shift so that it's funny
you asked that because I feel like I'm
back in my dissertation defense in
graduate school um but I think that's
where the power of genetics and like our
these genetic screening tools come into
play is
in this circumstance, why not
pre-seelelect people who are more
optimal at night um for these types of
positions? Um I I know it
like in medicine like that might be a
little bit more controversial but again
like going back to communities like
where the ones I work in is like I would
want to have people who are good at
operating at night to win our nation's
wars to reduce casualties to you know
increase combat effectiveness things
like that are there tools to screen for
that do you know are there are there
markers are there tests can we do where
if somebody wants to just do this on
their own so they want to figure out
Hey, um, I'm considering taking this
job. It's a night shift job or not.
Like, I want to know if I'm there. Do
you know of any effective tools for that
stuff? I mean, you just spit in a tube
and send it off to the lab for analysis.
It's that's all it is. I mean, there's
robust known genetic markers, you know,
single nucleotide polymorphisms that are
linked to being a morning person, an
evening person. I mean, we know those
per two snips. That's the that's the
gene, the circadian clock gene per two
per two. Um, and that can be any genetic
company or is there a particular ones
that that sell kits that test for these
that are better than others? To the best
of my knowledge, most of these genetic
screening companies will will test for
this snip. Okay. And it is it's uh
almost as simple as that one marker that
is. Yeah. Well, it is because that's
what you know what's been identified in
pre-clinical animal models and again has
been shown in large scale um genome
genomicwide studies in humans is yeah
changes in the circadian clock genes.
Which one was that one again? Just uh
per two per two. Okay. So per two is uh
associated with an evening chronotype
and per one is associated with a morning
chronotype. What percentage of people
are evening versus morning versus
somewhere in the middle? So we know most
of this not from the genetic work but
from this robust questionnaire that's
been around for honestly 40 years. It's
called the morning eveningness
questionnaire. I mean there's a a newer
modified version of this that um Dr.
Till Roenberg has created to uh include
social influences. Um but based on just
again largecale epidemiological
population based studies of this
questionnaire about 80% of us are
intermediate types meaning right we
normally go to bed or prefer to go to
bed around 1000 p.m. wake up around 6:00
a.m. Yeah. You have 10% of the
population who are like me who are more
evening types. Now, I'm not an extreme
evening type. I feel like I used to be.
Uh but as I've gotten older, right, my
clock is now phase advancing like most
people when they age. Yeah. Um who
prefer to go to bed around midnight,
12:30, wake up 8, 8:30. And then the
other 10% are these people like you who
are the morning types who prefer to go
to bed at 9:00 and wake up at 4:00 a.m.
You know, that's how my wife is. It's I
would like to go to bed earlier than
that, but yeah, nine o'clock. We'll just
say nine o'clock. Yeah. Yeah. If you ask
my wife, she'd be like, "Is your wife a
night owl?" No, she's more of a night
owl. She was when like when we first
met, she was uh 11:30, like 11, right?
Wake up at 6:00 sort of thing. And now
over the years, like she's drifted way
down towards me where she's there. I'm
definitely like if I especially if I
didn't have kids, like 8:00 I'm in bed.
Yeah. Like a thousand%. And she's just
like, "No, like not going to happen."
Like get up, we have to go do whatever.
the the likelihood of us like watching a
movie or something after the kids go to
bed, zero. Like it's just not going to
happen. It's funny because um well I'm a
geo bachelor but like when I do get to
spend some time with my wife it's the
same way. It's just I have to like
motivate her to I am your wife
essentially. Like I have to motivate my
wife to like a 4hour shift between you
guys when you want to get up and do
stuff. Yeah. Where I am in North
Carolina and she's in Florida. Um, by
the time she's going to bed, I am which
is around like 7:45 8. I am just leaving
the gym to go home and eat dinner and
have an extra two 2 and 1/2 hours of my
day before I go to bed. Are you like my
wife where we will be silent for like 30
minutes? Mhm. Like in bed or whatever
and I'm like finally like time to go to
sleep and then some like there has to be
some deep conversation happen like it's
just like a like talk about some big
thing. I'm like, "Oh my god." Like, but
she's like always does that. It's It's a
bad cliche, but are you are you like
that, too? I I am. Yes. Yeah. And she's
just like, "Stop." Like, "Stop talking
to me." Yeah. And then I'll just like
drift off into sleep in the middle of
the conversation. Oh, I'm gone. Like,
I'm definitely gone in that
conversation. It's like so many times
I've fallen asleep in the middle of her
story because I'm just like, I can't.
Yeah. I'm done for. Yep. No, that's
Yeah, that's me, too. All right. I fit
that stereotype. Fantastic. Yeah. I was
asking you earlier about people that
have this uh not quite polyphasic but
multiple sleep several hours of sleep
throughout the day. Yeah. In the world
I'm coming I come from that's often
because of sunlight, right? Where you're
you're out doing stuff. Yep. You head
back towards camp and then by the time
you get back and do stuff and then you
only have four hours or five hours
before you got to get back up again,
feed the horses, do things. Yeah. So you
can get out before sunrise, right? Yep.
So then you have three to four hours of
sleep and you're going to sleep more
there. Yeah. I know you've done a bunch
of work in of course the military, tons
of groups in there. You've done stuff
with astronauts, right? You've done
stuff in Antarctica, right? So how do
you handle it when you have when light
is either not the queue, it's not there
at all times, you're up in space, it's
there at all times. How do you manage a
sleep schedule when light is completely
eliminated from the equation or maybe
not eliminated but you know what I mean
like it's completely off of schedule?
Yeah. So that's actually what speaks
to
the robustness of the sleep system is
like work in these extreme environments
and I'll use our study in Antarctica as
an example. So honestly to date that is
probably the coolest project that I got
to be a part of. How could it not be?
Um, so we did essentially a year-long
longitudinal assessment of sleep down.
Um, it's it was actually in
collaboration with the Argentinian Navy.
Uh, so they have this Navy base down
there called Belgron 2 and it's actually
the southernmost point in the world. Uh,
and what's interesting is six months of
the year like they have access, it's
kind of like being stationed on the
International Space Station is you have
access to food, water, resources, and
then medevac. Uh but the other six
months of the year if something happens
medically they have to figure it out,
right? So there's a lot of stress during
the winter because they don't have
access to food resources or any contact
with the outside human world. You can't
get a plane in and out because of
weather. You can't Yeah. Because of the
weather. Um and so what we did was we
used acttographs which you know still
are clinical grade measures of sleep.
Two weeks worth of acttograph data
translates to a night of um in in a
sleep lab. So a night of polyynography.
Yeah. This is this is a wrist wearable.
Exactly. And and and it's extremely
durable. I mean we've taken these
wearables out into combat zones um and
they've come back working completely
fine. So uh they're made to withstand
these extreme conditions. And what we
found
is the structure of sleep across this
time being stationed in Antarctica does
change from the summer to the winter. So
for example, in the winter there's fewer
sleep episodes, but the sleep episodes
are longer. And then in the summer
there's more sleep episodes, but the
sleep episodes are shorter. But when you
look at overall daily 24-hour sleep
amounts, they're the same winter versus
summer. And what's really interesting is
that also lends to changes in um
physiology, blood pressure um and
cognitive performance too. So we also
measured blood pressure down there. So
we did
um four times a day they did blood
pressure measurements because they
wanted to catch like you know predicted
times of the circadian peak versus
circadian trough. Um and then same with
the gold standard for vigilance which is
the psycho motor vigilance test. Oh
yeah. Like none of these parameters
change seasonally. And I do believe it's
because of the fact that like under you
know complete observational
um study that the sleep system didn't
change regardless of what was changing
in the environment. Like that's just how
robust our sleep system is. Biology
figured it out. Exactly. Yeah, it got
there. Right. Yeah. We talk a lot about
when we coach people, we we try to avoid
using sleep optimization, right? What we
really try to go after is sleep
resilience. Yeah. Right. I want you to
be able to have effective quality sleep
independent of all these things. I I
think one of the things we have helped
people with a lot is I don't want you to
have to have a 90minute routine and a
45minute breath work session and have
everything perfect for you to have a
reasonable night of sleep. Mhm. You
become super sensitive, right? We will
need to be more resilient against that.
Sounds like that's exactly what you're
talking about, that anarchist. Yeah. And
so, um I mean, so back in the the
military sleep lab, we've done these
types of studies, too, right? Because
we've done very well controlled um
either acute sleep deprivation to mimic
combat operations like what we're
exposed to when we're deployed or uh
chronic sleep loss. And we actually find
when you go back to self-report
um even if someone had a really poor
night of sleep objectively, right? But
they are convinced that they got
restorative sleep or that they have high
sleep resil resiliency, their next day
performance on objective tasks such as
the psychoot vigilance tests will be
better than someone who rates themsel as
not being resilient to sleep
deprivation. So, you know, you go back
to that debate of biology versus
psychology. I mean, I yes, I still sit
in the biological camp, but I understand
there are psychological influences.
Don't you waver on me, Dr. Breaker. No,
no, no, no. How long is that tail going
to last? In other
words, I mean, you've been outspoken
about this. There's a difference between
clinical deficiencies, right?
Whether this is because you have a sleep
disorder or because you're in a special
situation where you legitimately have
sleep restriction, whatever's going on,
going from that to okay sleep is not the
same thing as going from good to great
sleep, right? And there's huge
performance advantages of going from
good to great sleep. Yep. But at the
same time, you also just told me even if
I have a terrible night of sleep, if I
think I'm okay, I perform the best. So
if I sleep like [__] all the time, if I
just think I'm fine, am I going to be
okay? Like where where's the line here?
You know what I like what's the where's
the breaking point? I I will say with
confidence just from the studies we've
done the breaking point is 72 hours. So
yeah yeah it is a very shortterm effect
I will say. Um and you know to quote
like the godfather of sleep medicine at
Stanford University Dr. William C.
Dement who uh passed away two years ago
at the age of 98. He used to say like
sleepiness makes you stupid because it
is true. It's like this false sense that
you're okay, but objectively you're
performing horribly. And that's really
what we see like in studies we've done
and then even those endocrine studies
where you're getting insufficient sleep
and there's an immediate drop off in
circulating levels of testosterone. By
day three, the system is at its max. Um,
I mean, we even found that with a study
my my colleague uh Dr. Tracy Jill Dodie
did um back at Walter Reed where
essentially caffeine will help stabilize
your cognitive performance under
insufficient sleep up to 3 days and then
after that caffeine stops working. Like
there's no amount of caffeine that can
replace lost sleep. Only sleep can
replace lost sleep. So it would be fair
then to characterize it as saying have
if you have a bad night of sleep or two,
don't worry about it. Yeah. Past that
though, we need to start making changes.
Exactly. Yep. And that's um you know, I
get asked this question all the time. Is
it good to keep the same sleep schedule
like say you're getting insufficient
sleep on the weekdays versus you know,
keeping that same schedule on the
weekends. I come from the camp that like
I believe in sleep banking and trying to
replace sleep pressure or build up on
anticipated
um sleep pressure as much as possible.
So for me, I work with populations where
they're getting insufficient sleep
during the work week. And so they need
to disrupt their circadian rhythm on the
weekend to bank on that sleep to uh make
up for loss sleep, but also prepare them
for the week ahead. Um and there is some
data now, I know there's a study that
came out a few months ago. Um again
large-scale population study that found
that people who sleep in on weekends um
if they are getting insufficient sleep
on weekdays have a 20% reduction in uh
risk for cardiovascular disease. Are
there frameworks in which you can do it
where it doesn't mess up circadian
rhythm. So the obvious example would be
and you're not saying this to be clear.
If you wake up at 5 in the morning
during the week, then hey, it's okay to
stay up till four o'clock at night on
the weekends as long as you sleep till
noon. That that's not what you're
saying. No, I'm not. Clarify what you
mean by like banking or extending out on
the weekend so we don't get
misinterpretations here. Yeah, that is
true. So, um, what I mean is you're
going to keep one of those things the
same usually, right? You hope so. Yeah.
So, in this circumstance, if you're
going if you're waking up at 5:00 a.m.
and say you're going to bed at 11:00
p.m. on the weekdays, then if you go to
bed at 11:00 p.m. on Friday night and
Saturday night, but now you're sleeping
in until 8 or 9. That's what I'm talking
about. So, you're keeping one of the two
things consistent. Now, I don't think
this would probably work in people who,
you know, use Friday night, go to the
club, stay up really late, um, and then
try to sleep in. Um, I mean, I know in
the the clinical world when you look at
like, um, cognitive behavioral therapy
for insomnia, for example, um, when
those behavioral sleep medicine
physicians are trying to extend sleep,
um, they do it in 30 minute intervals.
So that is something we do know about
the circadian clock is that um you can
do things in 30 minute increments over
an extended period of time to reduce the
amount of physiological stress on the
system. I wanted to actually ask about
on a similar note sleep in space. Okay.
Um I know you're in the process of
hopefully becoming an astronaut
yourself. Hopefully. Yes. You're waiting
back on that. We'll see. Maybe maybe
we'll have you back after you spent a
year in space. But um how do you think
about how do how do we handle sleep in
spacing and when we've lost not only
light but a thousand other cues? Yeah.
Um so first question on this. Do people
in space sleep okay? Is it a huge
problem? What's it look like up there?
So anecdotally from what I've heard it
it depends. So, um, for example, um,
Colonel Frank Rubio, uh, we had him, uh,
he actually gave a a leadership lecture
to those of us at work from the
International Space Station when he was
waiting to come home because, as you
know, he was up in space for the longest
of any human ever um, at the in the
International Space Station. He said he
slept great. How long was he up there
for? It was over a year. Way over a
year. Yeah. Yeah, like I understand like
that the psychological Yeah. uh demands
the current astronauts are facing right
now is difficult, but you know, he talks
about that as well, just you know,
missing important family events and what
whatnot. But he said that he slept great
in space. Um I've met a few other
astronauts who said that it was the
opposite for them. And then there's
lingering effects back on planet Earth
such as um difficulties with injuries
and maintenance of REM sleep for
example. Um, it makes sense to me in
terms of a microgravity environment
impacting sleep
because just like with other sensory
systems of the nervous system, what is
this the epicenter of sleep maintenance
and sleep continuity is the phalamus,
right? The phalamus is the gateway for
sensory information.
uh and there's a direct connection
between your vestibular balance system
and the phalamus that's going to
influence sleep states. Um I mean again
this hasn't really been studied at a
deep physiological level in space but
hypothetically what we know about the
circuitry of the vestibular system and
how it synapses on the phalamus that's
what I predict is what's influencing
these um changes in sleep architecture
with uh microgravity.
They have light taken care of for the
most part. Correct. Yeah. They have I
mean that's one thing is a lot of what
we know about the influence of flight
and photoic information on human
physiology behavior and performance
actually comes from honestly NASA. Um
they have a really fantastic crew and
they always have of like sleep and
circadian fatigue scientists. Um my
friend Dr. um Aaron Flynn Evans. She's
one of the main fatigue scientists for
NASA. And she comes from that, you know,
body of training at Stanford and Harvard
um who, you know, have been the founding
fathers and mothers of of sleep
physiology and medicine. What do they do
for physical sleep? Are they tying them
down to the side of the space station so
they're not floating around? Like what
is actually happening? Because to your
point about the phalamus, when when you
just look at pressure differences,
right? There's a physical pressure that
changes when you spend your entire day
erect and then you go horizontally,
right? Fluid shifting. You have a whole
host of things that are happening. This
is one of the things that's actually
I've seen in the research recently about
problems with sleep related obesity that
are not just airway blockage, right? You
have fluid shifting. You have other
things that are going on that are real
problems. So, how do they handle that
stuff? Do they sleep horizontally? That
wouldn't matter, right? So, my
understanding is they're
sleeping vertically and it's like you're
velcroed in essentially. So, it's
um that's that's my understanding of it.
So, I know I'll report back to you once
I'm up there. I want direct report. We
want to actually do a a follow-up
episode from the Well, they do. So when
I went for selection the first time and
we went to uh mission control, there is
a phone and you know their day is very
structured and scheduled but they do
have time where they can use this phone
in the space station and call down to
like their family and they'll use it to
like watch a movie and stuff with their
family. So nice. Yeah, I'll use that
time for a podcast. Perfect. Well, I'm
going to hold you to that.
Have you thought at all about sleep in
Mars? Yeah, I mean I have. So that's um
that's why I think it's going to be
personally like more important than ever
for NASA if we want Mars to actually be
a viable feasible thing. You are going
to need physicians and you are going to
need scientists and obviously engineers
right behind that to lead that mission.
Um
because you know physiology in extreme
environments as we just talked about
with the work we've done in Antarctica
even all the work we've done in in
active combat zones in the military is
it is very different um and we need to
understand those nuance differences um
and also understand nuance differences
between men and women right because it's
going to have an impact there do you
think it could be part of the screening
process for those folks that go out
there so oh absolutely I I mean, I think
when it comes for training for Mars and
and full disclosure, so the class of
astronauts that um I was part of in
2020, like that first class selected um
is hypothetically the first class to
prepare for um Martian
exploration.
Um I think they're going to look at
health above all else. I mean skill set
and talent is important but I feel as if
the talent is less important than
finding an incredibly healthy person who
does not have any family history of any
disease whatsoever or just is you know
genetically very healthy. So I've been
saying for a long time Mars is not going
to be a rocket problem. It's a
physiology problem. It's a physiology
problem. Absolutely. Yep. What would you
do personally to prepare for that? Would
you just figure it out along the way or
is there any sleep resilient stuff you
could do? Is there any different
training or any other stuff you would do
in preparation for Mars? I don't know if
this sounds far-fetched, but I wouldn't
treat it any differently than these, you
know, pre-clinical mouse model
transgenic studies we used to do, right?
or I have done is you have to first
understand the physiology and behavior.
Uh you have to break it down and then
again study sex differences in this
behavior because it's going to impact
males and females differently. Um and
then that's where you use the power of
pharmaceutical,
neutrautical and genetic interventions.
I mean even to the point of I think it's
necessary and sufficient at this point
to use things like crisper and gene
editing to like I mean it it becomes
like the ultimate biology physiology
problem having that
opportunity to explore Mars. I mean,
sure, you want these people to live
long, healthy lives after they're done
with the space program, but at the end
of the day, you also have this person
who has this mentality that they're
willing to be like yeated off the planet
um into the unknown. So, you know, I
feel like people like me who are
willing, you know, and who have wanted
to be an astronaut like their whole
life, you know, we're we're willing to
accept some pharmaceutical or
neutrautical or genetic interventions
um in order to get the job done. Yeah. I
mean, I guess what you're saying is if
you're 95% of the way there and there's
just a couple of things that are
stopping you, why not exactly take those
and get all the way out there? Yeah.
Exactly. Well, I fully support that. Do
you know of any um animal models that
are doing things like that like gene
editing? Uh probably obviously not for
Mars but for other aspects of sleep. Are
you aware of any clinical trials
happening or people tinkering with that
or labs that are working on stuff? So in
regards to space exploration I don't
know that but I will say like crisper
and gene editing to better understand
fle sleep physiology has been a thing.
Um I think that's really what you see
now. Um when you look at like the
evolution of using pre-clinical animal
models to understand mamian physiology
is behavior, right? It's like I came
from the generation where we were still
working with these transgenic mouse
models. Um you know just through
sophisticated breeding of hetererozygous
and homozygous mice to hope and pray you
get the genotype based on Darwinian you
know hereditary genetics that you are
hoping for. Now we can actually go in
and directly manipulate the genome uh
through gene editing or um like in as a
postoc when we were doing that skeletal
muscle physiology project we were using
um a transgenic mouse model where we
just had to give the mouse doxycyc so
the antibiotic to either turn on or turn
off genes. Oh because you had already
put something in there and you just had
to activate it. I didn't put it in
there, but the you know the group at
Southwestern that had created these
genetic mouse models. Yeah, that's a
whole another world of like molecular
genetics that I don't understand and I
just really appreciate that they're
clever and intelligent enough to do
something like that. But, you know,
there
are a number of people who sleep poorly
and there's a select number of people
who sleep horribly but somehow get away
with it. Mh. Right. And you talked about
earlier and I know that there's plenty
of studies that look at a lot of people
who think they're getting away with it
aren't. Right. So cognitive function is
way lower even u despite people's
perception Yeah. of their cognitive
performance. Right. They're like
significantly lower. That's that's been
shown many many times. Right. So we
argue this all the time when you're like
if we look at your data and your your
numbers are not great but you think and
your perception is high there's a good
chance that it's not actually as as high
as you think. Yep. But there are those
select few, right? Those people who can
get away with a few hours of sleep per
night, right? Four or five or probably
is probably more appropriate. Do you
think it's realistic at all for us to be
able to engineer something like that?
So, could we figure how how much do we
know about the genes behind those? Is
there a phrase for people that sleep for
four hours a night and actually like get
away with what do we call them? I mean,
we could uh so they're short sleepers.
Short sleepers. Yeah. So um that gene
was isolated and discovered in a
pre-clinical mouse model and again
population uh genomewide study uh in
humans I'd say 1015 years ago. It's
called the deck gene DEEC. Um so those
are individuals who are able to sleep
four hours. Um, again, hypothetically,
what I think is going on is like they're
reducing their extracellular adenosine
really quickly because that's really
what it is is like how quickly can you
reduce sleep pressure? That's what
determines your physiological set point
for sleep. So, I need for example
myself, I'm like an 8.2, probably 8 and
1 half hour sleeper. So I know my sleep
pressure dissipates very very slowly but
in these individuals it dissipates very
quickly. How much actual work has been
done on those individuals in terms of
physical performance? Obviously we know
like long-term they don't die earlier
that's like the clinical markers we
have. Yeah. But are they really
physically performing at their best or
their cognitive function is high? Like
is there actually been reasonable
research on that? No, there hasn't. I
mean I would love if I had money to do
that work I would. I mean like US
presidents are a great example like just
historically anecdotally what we know
about most US presidents is they don't
really sleep a lot but again they were
sort of you know self- selected it just
I would say the same with military
leaders right they're self- selecting
because of genetics like when you get to
that level I think we know this in
sports too right that's why one of my
favorite books is the sports gene um
because it really talks about how your
genetic blueprint can sort of guide you
into what sport you play and what sport
you excel in. I know that there was
actually some stuff that came out
recently on uh President Trump and they
were able to assess his sleep duration
simply by his online activity. Oh yeah,
I do remember that. Yeah. Right. So like
he's one of these guys that apparently
legitimately does and I know there's
there's lots of um lots of people talked
about President Obama as well as like
working these right Stanley Mcrist like
Admiral Mcrist was known to be a two
three hour sleeper I mean I see that
even in my own workplace too right like
folks you work with
is there a way that you could get to
that right so kind of what I'm getting
at on the back of that thing is saying
like hey can
we number one be more resilient be more
efficient and then will that actually
allow me to shorten my hour demands down
to a reasonable. Is that what's
happening with these presidents? Are
they just hyper efficient? Is their
sleep architecture? Is their sleep
resilience? Is their sleep stability
just way higher or are they kind of the
same and it doesn't matter? It's actual
presidents, right? It's just people that
that get away with it or they just the
same and they just can get away with way
less hours. No, it's more efficient,
right? Because that's what the again
these preclinical animal models that we
can glean into is like the sleep
pressurees dissipated really quickly. So
there's uh a significant increase in
slowwave activity um very quickly and
it's extended for a period of time um
because that at the end of the day
that's the manifestation of dissipated
sleep pressure is stage three non-REM
sleep or slowwave activity um but I do
think it's one of those things again it
has to be guided through the lens of
biology and it can't be trained right is
because it breaks down to differences is
and the um architecture of the neur
neuronal circuitry and the
neurochemistry. Um and I don't think any
amount of training or you know
behavioral intervention could
um lead to a physiological change of
that significant capacity. Too much just
indogenous natural function. Exactly.
That have to be manipulated. Let's go
the opposite direction. Okay. Sleeping a
lot. Mhm. Um, you have made the case, I
have made the case that high performers,
you're probably looking at more like
eight and a half to nine, maybe nine and
a half hours of sleep, right? And that's
been shown many, many times. Yep. I'm
going to spend a lot of time on that.
But before we get there, really quickly,
what about past that point? What do we
know about people sleeping routinely 9
and a half hours, 10 hours?
Usion is that's not a good thing. Yeah.
So actually my buddy Michael Graner at
the University of Arizona, he's looked
at that, right? It's like it's not good
to be on either tail end. So insomnia,
hyperomnia as it's called is just as bad
as insomnia. And if you look at
morbidity and mortality in those
individuals who get who need 10 11 hours
of sleep because their rate of
dissipating sleep pressure is just so
low
like they suffer from the same health
outcomes as someone who obviously
willingly short changes their sleep
because of life. Why does somebody need
10 10 and a half 11 hours of sleep? Is
that a insanely inefficient sleep
pattern or are they sleeping that
because of other reasons?
Um I guess another way to think about it
is when they wake up the next day and
they still feel tired, right? It's like
I slept nine hours, I still feel tired.
Yeah, probably something is happening I
assume, right? Yeah. I mean my
assumption is there's there there's a
physiological disruption there mixed
with for example we know people who are
clinically depressed for example um do
fall in this category of hyperinsomnia
um and so um and and some of that again
can be is physiologically rooted um but
you know compounded by life trauma too
that's could be contri contributing to
that clinical depression. Um, but that's
where I think we most often times see um
these issues with hyperinsomia is
they're usually also associated with
some sort of um mental health condition
as well, particularly clinical
depression. Interesting. Or someone with
chronic pain like fibromyalgia for
example. Yeah, that makes sense. How
much do we know if any about cause and
effect there? Which direction? Oh, that
is like that is still to this date a
constant debate in the sleep medicine
community. So, um I've been going to the
annual sleep medicine conference now
since 2006. I've only missed one. That
was the year I was competing in the
CrossFit games. Um but besides that,
like that's still one of the
centerpieces
um of the meeting is like is chicken or
the egg? Is it the sleep manifestation
of then depressive symptoms or do the
depressive symptoms contribute to the
sleep symptoms? And every year there's
new data presented uh not just in
pre-clinical animal models but in human
studies as well that no it's it's so
complicated and nuanced. Um and even
with you know the ability
to effectively treat clinical depression
now not just with pharmaceuticals but
also with um for example um transranial
electrical stimulation or transmetic
stimulation. Um there's still just not a
consensus in terms of you know is it the
sleep or is it the depression.
Um more than likely it's a combination
of both. It's got it's got to be right
in some people. You could certainly see
a bunch of chronic poor sleep led to
poor health effects. And certainly you
can see the opposite something else
happened in life created mental health
concerns and then because of that you
can't sleep. Like you could certainly
see the only reality here is there's
room for both. Yep. Like both are are
potential causes. So trying to isolate
and say one is always driving the other
one is is it's honestly it's quite
nonsensical right now where we're going
to go. Yeah. I mean, we see the same
thing, you know, use uh in my community
with traumatic brain injury. It's like
we know from the clinical studies, like
this one study we did at Walter Reed,
that if you have a mild, even just a
mild traumatic brain injury, it's going
to lead to long-term changes in sleep
architecture. Um, but then you have all
the lifestyle factors that
uh also are influenced by that, right?
like using alcohol to cope with the lack
of sleep or difficulties with sleep now
that weren't in existence prior to
traumatic brain injury. Um the inability
to regulate stress and how because of
that inability to regulate stress that's
going to impact sleep. It's right. You
can never have things in isolation.
Today's episode is sponsored by
Momentus. Momentous makes the highest
quality supplements on the market.
Period. Many of you know me and you know
that I do not trust the vast majority of
supplement companies. And for good
reason. Many studies have shown that
anywhere between 10 to up to 40% of
supplements have accidental
contaminants, intentional alterations,
mislabeling, or other serious issues.
But Momentus is different. I literally
spent years vetting the company, their
products, and leadership team before
personally officially partnering with
them in 2023. Every single one of
Momentous's products is third-party
tested to ensure quality, and many are
even NSF certified for sport. Now, while
I love all of their products, the ones I
use the most, both personally and with
my clients are what I call the big
three. And these are the omega-3 fish
oil, creatine, and newly improved whey
protein formula. These three supplements
have fantastic data supporting their
benefits. whey protein for lean muscle
mass, omega-3s for brain health, and
creatine for both muscle and brain
support. And they have been shown to be
very safe across basically all
populations of people, young, old, men,
women, etc. Now, nobody has to use
supplements, and I hope you never feel
pressured to do so. But if you're
interested in supplements, it's
important that you get them from the
highest quality providers. You don't
want mercury in your fish oil or lead in
your whey protein or anything like that.
So that's why I stick exclusively to
Momentus. If you'd like to give Momentus
a try, go to live
momentous.comperform to get 20% off your
order. Again, that's live
momentous.com/perform to get 20%
off. How do we create more efficient
sleep? So when somebody says, Allison,
I've got A and B job. Whether it's going
on like six and a half, seven is just
the most realistic thing. Can I get more
efficient in that time? Yep. And I'll
give you a little bit of a pass here.
You can skip past all the basic hygiene
stuff, right? Like cold, dark, room.
Yeah, we get it. All that. Yeah. Yeah.
What past that can we do? I mean, I
think that's where the circadian system
really takes over, right? Like I talked
earlier about these time cues or
zeitgeabers. Yeah. When you have
predictable time cues in your
environment, uh, and this isn't just a
human. And I mean we see this in in
mouse and rodent models as well. Once
that time Q is presented that behavior
will then follow that time Q. Um so if
you are eating at a particular time um
if you're engaged in social stimuli at a
particular time if you're viewing
sunlight at a particular time then at
night right if you're now exposed to
dimmer light at a particular time you
have eaten dinner at a particular time
and then whether you have a sleep
hygiene routine or not but you are now
going to bed at a particular particular
time like your brain will now
consolidate sleep into that period of
time. I work with a bunch of
entrepreneurs, a bunch of business
owners, uh, e executives for sport teams
and things like this, right? We get this
question constantly. So, let me frame
you with a theoretical that's actually
not at all a theoretical. I just don't
want to say the person's name example.
And, uh, I'm going to give you a ton of
incomplete information, okay? But just
do your best to what what something
could look like. I will also give you
more caveats for you. This is maybe not
the optimal system or best system, but
hopefully what you'll provide for us is
just one example of what it could look
like. Yeah. Fair game. Sure. All right.
Awesome. So, you got an individual and
they're going to flat out say midnight
is when I'm going to go to bed and I got
to be up at 6. Okay. That's that's the
rules of the game period, right?
Whatever it takes. Um, I will get into
bed at about
11:50 and the alarm is off at 6:00 and
I'm and I'm getting up and out of bed
period. Yep. I have hundreds of millions
of dollars, closer to billions actually
on the line. Mhm. So, I need my
cognitive function to be at its highest.
I want to perform well physically, but
that's my second year priority. Right.
Yeah. So cognitive function is this
person's top, but we'll not accept low
energy, will not accept terrible
physical performance in the gym. Yep. Is
going to train every day. We'll do some
conditioning. We'll do some lifting. Do
a variety of stuff. Right. Uh also has
children. Mhm. Right. So we'll pay
attention to the children from like 3 to
8:00 or so. And then because he's
working with kids from 3 to 8 or playing
with his kids and being very present,
he's definitely going to go back to work
at 8:00. Yeah, it's going to happen,
right? Um 8 to 10:30 or so, maybe up to
11 is back to work and then 11 to
midnight is shower wife situation. Uh
before I start asking you questions, any
more critical information you have to
know about this person? I do want to
know if they think they're a morning or
evening person. Um this person will tell
you doesn't matter. Doesn't matter.
Okay, they're whatever is going to take
to make this is the schedule. Um, but I
would say has he's certainly
self-induced himself to be a morning
person whether he is there or not. Like
Gotcha. That's the think very much
military business like you got to be in
the office by seven. Like that's just
what you sort of do. Yeah. Yeah. Gotcha.
Um, stimulants are on board,
pharmaceuticals are on board, don't
care. Uh, doesn't drink alcohol
excessively, but whatever it takes to
perform the best. Doesn't want to
compromise long-term health. Doesn't
want to die earlier. Any of those
things. Yeah. Um, but if you say take a
take melatonin, great. If you say don't
take melatonin, great. You say drink
caffeine, great. Like, doesn't care.
Whatever it's going to take to get the
job done. Okay. So, that said, um, let
let me just do like a theoretical kind
of highlevel thing, waking up at 6,
anything that he should particularly
take, do, don't do for the first, I'd
say he'd give you 45 minutes in the
morning, right? Anything that would jump
out on your list of like critical stuff
to do at that time frame to get going
cognitively. Well, since stimulants are
uh allowed, I mean caffeinate, right?
Because what we know from our clinical
studies is the easiest way to reduce
sleep inertia in the morning that
groggginess is to caffeinate as soon as
possible. As soon as possible, less less
than 200 milligrams because 200
milligrams we know from our randomized
clinical trials. We've done numerous
circumstances under conditions of acute
sleep deprivation, chronic sleep
deprivation. Um, even looking at
genotype, for example, 200 milligrams is
the ceiling effect for caffeine. So like
two cups of black coffee. So if you go
to three or 400, you're just hitting the
gas pedal. You're not going Yeah. It's
right. Okay. So 200 um within the first
few minutes of getting up, correct?
Anything else? I mean, obviously
sunlight. Yeah. Right. That's a that's a
given. Um he'll work out whatever time.
He'll work out in the morning, he'll
work out in the afternoon, whatever.
When should he train?
So that's why I asked if morning person,
evening person.
Um, I mean, if I was him, I would
probably train in the morning, right?
Because now you're capitalizing on that
rise in cortisol. So you're going to
optimize your training um more so than
you would in the afternoon. And then
you're going to get that extended, you
know, cognitive mood energy to be more
productive in uh the latter half of your
your morning. um as your cortisol
continues to rise. Okay, makes sense.
Anything else we should consider in the
morning or should we move throughout the
day? I would say during that time too
it, you know, depending on where this
individual lives like vitamin D
supplementation. I mean, even if you are
getting natural sunlight, uh you know,
if you're up in Boston or New York, uh
like a lot of Wall Street executives,
it's not, you know, it's good to
supplement with vitamin D. Okay. Um,
anything he should be doing specifically
throughout the day or not doing until
that 3:00 uh goes gets kids and sort of
all there. So again, um, with strategic
caffeine dosing, that's why, you know,
we had done all those studies uh, in
randomized clinical trials. So you can
supplement with 200 milligrams of
caffeine every four to six hours as
needed. Mhm. Um, you can even do 2 to 4
hours as needed, stopping at least 6 to
8 hours before bedtime. Okay. So, he'd
be good to take uh he could have his
6:00 caffeine and then maybe have it
again at noon. Or even like 9:00 in the
morning if he wants and do it again at
noon, right? And then maybe uh maybe
even again at like 3:00 or 4.
As long as Yeah. Because that's within
the 8 hour time window before before
midnight. Yeah. Before midnight. Okay.
Um, he's going throughout the day. He's
going to go back to work, like I said,
at 8:00. Yep. And he's not going to stop
until an hour before. Mhm. He goes to
bed. Are they any best practices? Any
things he can do either during that
3-hour work window or right after it?
What can he do to make sure that when he
gets into bed at 11:50, he is asleep by
midnight or close to it and has the
highest quality six hours possible?
Well, so that's why like he's not going
to have it like a full-on sleep hygiene
routine. And here's the thing, that
sleep hygiene routine, that 90-minute
routine isn't necessary if you're
keeping everything else in your
environment consistent. Uh, but in order
to help facilitate that sleep, so you
have like a 10-minute sleep onset, um,
that's where I blue light blocking
glasses, right? as you're working.
That's what it I would have this
individual wear because now you're still
promoting that dim light melatonin onset
to then let that individual go to sleep.
So, while he's still aroused from work
activity, he can mitigate it some.
Exactly. Right. Because you're still
going to have brain activity and gamma
beta activity. It's not going to be
anywhere close to alpha, but um at least
you're you're not disrupting the dim
light melatonin onset through um not
having blue light blocking glasses.
Anything that uh he should take from a
food or a supplementation or drug or
anything. Maybe you don't have to go too
far into drug without knowing more
medical history there, but like Yeah. um
anything that you should take either you
know 8:00 9:00 midnight or right before
bed or or just sort of stay away as much
as you possibly can. So it is okay to
eat there are believe it or not
sleepromoting foods. So very recently
there was isolated a um uh protein
factor in believe it or not warm milk.
Warm milk. Warm milk that is
sleeppromoting. Um other sleepromoting
foods that have been studied in
randomized clinical trials include
things like um kiwis. Um well we already
talked about tart cherry extract. Um
that's good for skeletal muscle
recovery. So that's something I would I
would take. Y um in addition to to
working, right? Yep. Um any or a what do
you call um slow release protein like a
case and wave protein? Yeah. Yeah. Okay.
And any other um maybe are there any
common mistakes that they're making that
are that are maybe disrupting the sleep?
Um you know, we talked about melatonin
earlier, right? So what about chronic t
use of melatonin for someone like this?
is like, "Hey, I want to make sure I get
to sleep quickly, so I'm going to take
10 migs of mel melatonin every night."
Yeah, you don't need melatonin. And
actually, that melatonin will prevent
you from entering the restorative stages
of sleep. So, not a good So, yeah, at
night, like if you want to take anything
to help influence sleep maintenance, it
would be magnesium bioarbonate. Um, so a
powdered form of magnesium, it's going
to have greater bioavail availability.
Um but that would be a a good thing that
also helps offset um loading of the
central nervous system throughout the
day especially if this individual is you
know doing strength and conditioning as
part of their their physical fitness
routine. Um but no melatonin does not
work as a nighttime sleep aid. It acts
as a phase shifter. Yeah. But not as a
nighttime sleep aid. Yeah. and it can
have um negative impacts on sleep
architecture if not dosed appropriately.
What about any tools or technologies any
uh brainwave stuff he could do or not
do? You mentioned the shift wave chair
earlier, but anything else like that or
you feel like as long as you're like
this would be a pretty good setup for
this person if they keep having these
time cues and keep working in this
environment environment night after
night like again the brain will remember
and consolidate those time cues to then
help promote efficient sleep. So just
build the pattern. Yep. Exactly.
Patterns are everything. Yeah. Um I mean
I would say the last hack, right? Like
we talk about the cool, dark, quiet
room. Um, but believe it or not, taking
a hot shower before even like a
fiveminute hot shower before bed that's
going to right compensatory mechanism is
to cool you. So yeah, right. Don't cold
plunge before bed. I always tell people
that that is one
social norm that has become popular and
you know that mouth taping. So um tell
tell me about the cold plunging and
mouth taping. big fan of it, but it has
to be the right time of day. If you
think about it, right, you take a hot
shower, compensatory mechanism is your
body wants to cool down. Yep. Right. If
you cold plunge, compensatory mechanism
is your body wants to warm up. You don't
want to go into bed warm. You want to
think of sleep as a state of
hibernation. And essentially, that's
what happens at sleep, right? Is like
there's a significant drop in core body
temperature. And the greater the drop in
core body temperature, the greater the
propensity to spend in deep restorative
non-REM, right, and REM sleep, right?
Um, so mouth taping like general
consensus, American Academy of Sleep
Medicine, like understand that nasal
breathing is promoting the
parasympathetic nervous system. That's
fine. But if you're going to mouth tape,
like do it during the day to train your
diaphragm to activate appropriately to
then be able to breathe through your
nose at night and not your mouth when
you're asleep. The idea is right when
you're asleep, I mean, you're not
unconscious, but you're in a
subconscious state. Um, and you need
every bit of air you can get into your
system. And depending on what sleeping
position you're in, especially if you're
sleeping on your back or if you're
sleeping on your stomach, you're not
going to have the cool the full capacity
to activate your diaphragm to take in
air. So, if you're limiting the ability
to take in air through your mouth
because you don't have a well-trained
and strong diaphragm, then you're
setting yourself up for risk of apneaike
episodes, right? Um, what about nasal
dilators?
Oh, those are great. Yeah, any reduction
in mouth breathing and increase in nasal
breathing will promote restorative
sleep. Um, and nasal dilators can help
with that process. Okay. So, if you're
going to use something up there, opt
more towards just helping air flow
through the nose rather than blocking it
through your mouth. That's a better
approach. How did you handle the jet lag
last night? Right. How do how would this
guy or anybody else um when we're let's
just say that the normal person is, you
know, traveling once a month or so for
two or three days, right? And let's just
assume at least a three-hour change.
Obviously, if you're going a one hour
difference, it's not a big deal, but um
what can we do best to enhance? If you
don't want to call it jet lag, fine.
Like, because it's probably not that,
but you get it. Time shifting like that.
Multiple hours and I still got to do my
business meeting, I got to do my work, I
got to do whatever I perform the next
day. Well, it's a whole process, right?
And you know, I'll give a shout out to
my friend Andy uh uh who is the CEO of
Flykit uh or Fountain Bio. Um actually
his chief science officer Clayton and I
we started in the same sleep lab as
undergraduates at Brown University. Yes.
Such a it's such a small world in human
performance, but it was an intentional
process, right? Like so what's in this
fly kit is there are a certain pack of
supplements that promote um or that
reduce inflammation. Uh so combination
of fish oil, high dose vitamin B um part
cherry extract, things like that. Um I
also wore the blue light blocking
glasses that are in the kit on the
plane. Um you know I don't really watch
TV or movies. That's I know that seems
like I'm a weird like psychopath, but I
just used them and I was reading, right?
Um and then when I got to LAX um on the
way to the hotel, that's when I took the
melatonin. Uh but I only ever take
melatonin when I travel and that's only
within the first day or two um to help
coax my system into adjusting. But once
I'm adjusted, I stop taking melatonin.
How much do you take typically? What's
an effective dose for you? So uh
effective dose for me honestly is 1
milligram but like anything over three
is is that we find to like not it's the
ceiling effect really we've seen a lot
of people you'll see a lot of
recommendations of like five to 10.
Yeah. When we use it one would be about
the high end as well like it actually
really much more than that you're you're
not getting right really anything. We
stay pretty low also stays around. It's
supposed to have a halflife like
everything does, but when you
consistently dose it, it stays around
for a long time. Yeah. Oh, well, I will
tell you. So, I'm one of those believers
like I think Oliver Sax is like this.
Like he always in order to believe the
things he studied neurochemically, he
would take them themselves. So, I went
into since you went out to North
Carolina, I went into one of those um
country Dollar General stores, you know,
on the drive to work and I found a 20
Oh, a 20 block of melatonin. Oh, I took
it. Oh my god, I was [__] up for like
two days. Oh, I I believe you.
I don't Yeah, I do not care what I was
worried. I was actually worried at first
about taking it because I again I live
alone. So, I called my wife. I was like,
"Oh, honey, if I don't wake up in the
morning, like call 911." But I but they
literally It was a twob block pack, too.
So, like some idiot could have taken 40
of them. Yeah. Like 40.
That's so much. But I took the 20 and I
was It took me I was like brain dead for
two days. We used to measure I was
telling you this morning like we used to
measure uh urinary melatonin. So this is
a metabolite, right? It should be
metabolized. It should be very minimal.
We don't need more. But we did it and I
would probably say I don't know over 10
times we saw people that were 20 to 30x
upper range reference range values for
melatonin. And you're like whoa. Mhm.
Like we don't have any sleep problems to
fix here. The reason you feel like a
zombie all day is because you're
sedated. Yeah. Like you were sedated
with melatonin constantly. Yep. And just
removing melatonin from them, all of a
sudden all their years of sleep testing
issues. Yeah. Gone. Right. It's like
just gone. They're like, "Oh, you're
just walking around sedated." Yeah. And
plus too, they probably weren't getting
the effective entries into deep
restorative nonrem sleep, you know?
Nothing. Yeah. Yeah. Like they were on
the classic stimulant um sleep drug
cycle. Yep. Feel like terrible. Oh,
yeah. Yeah. Take a load of stimulants,
then you can't get to bed, so you take a
load of sleep, alcohol or Yeah. Just
break that cycle. So, let's talk about
sleep extension. Sure. Sleep banking.
What's the proper way to think about
this? Why do I even care about it? When
is the best way to use it? Who should be
thinking about it? Obviously, all of us
want to extend our sleep, right? Right.
Yeah. You have parents. It's like, yes,
I would love to sleep more. Not going to
happen.
So make your most convincing argument
for how much do I need here and what are
the best principles around sleep
extension. So again it's that 20 to 30
minute rule right because that if you're
extending sleep within a 20 to 30 minute
um period then it's not providing
additional physiological stress to the
circadian system. Right? because that's
that's a delicate balance of
uh maintaining or satisfying the sleep
homeostatic system which is sleep amount
and then circadian system which
obviously influences sleep quality. Y so
that's the one way to start. Now sleep
extension we use it in many different
forms. So napping serves as a form of
sleep extension right you use napping
essentially to repay off sleep debt. Um,
so if you're in an insufficient sleep
state, typically we would start with,
okay, take a 20 to 30 minute nap. Now,
if you can't nap, um, because you aren't
that person, then that's when we go to,
okay, let's either put you to bed 30
minutes earlier or extend your sleep by
30 minutes earlier um or later in the
morning. Um, again, that's done in a 30
minute interval. Um so typically what's
practiced and folks um who do cognitive
behavioral therapy for insomnia who are
trying to extend somebody's sleep is
they'll have that individual
um go to bed early 30 minutes or wake up
later 30 minutes uh for a period of a
week or two and then after that period
of time they extend it by 30 minutes
here and there. Um I know you've talked
about this before on the protocol. It's
it's physiologically impossible because
the circadian timing system will not let
you go from 5 hours to 8 hours. It is
not that simple. Um, you know, I see
this a lot with soldiers who I've
commanded and stuff who are now out of
the army and that's the question they
usually hit me up the most about is
like, "Hey ma'am, like I'm trying to get
eight or nine hours. I know I need that
and like why can't I just get eight or
nine hours?" person. So I have to like
explain to them this whole gradual
process and they're there now but it
took you know months you know six seven
months for them to get there. So usually
is it fair to
say 30 minutes per four weeks or 30
minutes per week like how how 30 minutes
per week. Yep. Is that Yeah. But even to
that that's going to have uh a ceiling
effect where at most you're probably
looking at extending sleep by two hours
at most. Y the other form of sleep
extension, and this is something that
we've studied in the lab, again, like we
do lab studies to mimic what possibly
could happen in combat situations, is
letting people sleep in for as long as
they want um past their normal bedtime.
So, usually we find that most people if
they have like a two-eek period to be on
their own, you know, or essentially like
say they're on vacation or the
equivalent of being in a scientific
study on vacation. Um, they'll sleep for
about anywhere from 45 minutes to an
hour past their normal bedtime. Um, and
then when you put those individuals
through a period of full-on sleep
deprivation, so we're talking about 40
hours of wakefulness all the way up to
62 hours of wakefulness sustained.
uh the rate of decline in their
cognitive performance, even their
physical performance, uh the rate of
decline is less because they had that
sleep on the front end um to help um
offset the um the sleep pressure. How
long do they have to bank that for? Is
that a two week? It's a two It's a It's
a 10-day protocol we were using. Yeah.
So sleep an extra hour or so for 10 days
and then if you were then to go into a
situation when you are literally awake
for 40 or 50 or 60 straight hours that
sleep deprivation is going to have
consequences. But what you're saying is
that sleep extension prior to means you
won't drop as far. Exactly. Now if
you're chronically insufficiently slept
uh before that point like you're
definitely going to drop. I can tell you
that from when I was deployed. So, we
did uh the longest I was awake was is
almost 3 days, but yeah, we were um
outside the wire with some people um and
I was awake for legitimately two days.
So, but that's where I used the
strategic caffeine dosing strategy for
the most part. I mean, I still felt like
I was completely drunk, right? You know,
the last 24 hours of being awake. Um,
but I used caffeine gum and yeah, even
tried dipping for the first time, which
uh it's disgusting. I hate that habit. I
uh I remember old hearing old stories of
people pilots. I think this was in World
War II where they would take tobacco and
put it like in their eyes. Oh wow. But
you know what? I mean, I'm not going to
lie, I felt like slightly ill after I
dipped for the first time and I felt I
had like a little buzz, but then that
sleep deprivation kicked in. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. How does the military handle it in
situations like that is just get through
it. Just do whatever it is just get
through it. You know, they are getting
smarter about it. Um I think that you
that's great about um you know the team
of individuals I've worked with over the
years is um that knowledge has now been
taken out to the field and and I mean
there's commanders out there who are now
using all these, you know,
evidence-based,
science-based DoD back science
principles to like be more effective in
combat. So it it is it's been really
cool. When it comes to sleep extension,
do people typically have an easier time
sleeping in or going to bed earlier? So
that's actually where I think
chronotype comes into play, right? Is so
for me, my sleep extension would be
right, sleep in later. Um for you, you
might want to go to bed early. That's
that's I would pick that a thousand
times over a thousand. Yeah. Every time.
Like sleeping in is a struggle to me.
Now,
albeit one of the things you just
mentioned earlier is something we hear
consistently, which is when people say,
"Oh, I can't sleep in." Mhm. It's
usually because they think that that's
going to happen tomorrow. Yeah. Right.
It's just like, "Oh, this thing
happened. I'm on vacation. Then like I
woke up early." Well, of course you did
because you've been sleeping. You've
been waking at that at that time for 400
consecutive days. Yeah. It's going to
take a few weeks for you to really
consistently be able to sleep in. Right.
Right. Yeah. So a sleep extension
protocol is unlikely to be like again
sleep in tomorrow. Yeah. When we've
worked with people and we're trying to
truly extend their baseline sleep. So
say they're getting an average of six
and a half hours. Yeah. We want to get
them to an average of seven. That is a
at least a two week thing. Yeah. That it
takes to get to that night after night.
As soon as you get off that schedule,
you got to restart. You know, we have
yet to find anybody who couldn't do it
if they zoom out on time frame. It is
usually I tried it, couldn't sleep in. I
tried it again today. It didn't work at
all. I just can't sleep in. Like, no.
No. Your your your physiology takes some
time, right? Yeah. To adjust. I mean,
that's the thing, right? A lot of people
want the quick fix, right? Um, you know,
just like it takes dedicated time to
build muscle. You just you have to trust
the process, right? Excellent. I got one
more question for you if uh you'd be so
kind. Sure. Maurice Clarrett. Um, oh,
okay.
Boom. Boom. Mancini. I could go on and
on. What the hell is in the water, in
the air? What is it about Youngstown?
Like, you come from this place. You were
uh uh I mean, you're still active. You
still do the CrossFit competitions. Um
first pole vault, female pole var in the
state of Ohio. In the state of Ohio.
Yep. I'm assuming then first to to go
compete collegially, um knocked on the
door of the Olympics. What is it in that
city? You guys just produce super
athletes for this random little city in
Ohio. What's going on there? It's so
funny you say that. Well, because you
know there's that 30 for30 documentary,
Youngtown Boys, right, with Jim
Trussell. And I don't think I realized
the community of athletics I grew up in
until I went to college. Like I thought
I was an average athlete, right? But
then, okay, let's unpack my high school.
Like I went to a big football feeder
school. Youngsttown Boardman. Bernie
Kosar went to my high school, right?
Yep. Yep. Um quarterback in our strength
and conditioning room in high school.
And we didn't have like really
phenomenal strength and conditioning
equipment. And in fact, I would say it
was kind of
like very bare bones equipment, but you
go into that strength and conditioning
room and you'll see like 50 people from
my high school who played in the NFL. I
mean, my graduating class alone, I
graduated with 711 kids. I would say 40
of them went on to play division one
sports, male and female. Actually,
that's underestimate. Probably like 60
or 70. Uh, one um almost made it to the
Olympics in swimming. We had a WNBA
player. And then, oh, we had three kids
in my graduating class who did actually
play in the NFL and won Super Bowl
rings. Yeah, it's outrageous. My
brother's class had an NFL player. I
mean, my So, my great uncle was a Golden
Gloves boxer. He actually um he refed a
Mike Tyson fight years ago. My other
great uncle, Lucy,
um he was a linebacker for the Giants.
Uh but yeah, it's like one of those
things you don't realize until you go to
college. You're like, "Shit, I actually
I guess I am an elite athlete, but I
always thought I was average because of
growing up there." It's It's insane how
what you think could be your baseline.
You go out into the world and you're
like, "Wow, I guess I you know, in this
one capacity, I am better than other
people." And I had no idea. I'm I'm
demanding more answers here. Uh my wife
went to Long Beach Poly, right? Modern
day. There's these schools in different
areas in Florida, stuff like, "Oh, yeah.
They put out 40 or 50 division one
athletes every year. Great. Well, you're
in LA. Yeah. Right. There's 3 million
people in a 20 mile radius. Yeah.
Youngsttown, Ohio. Like, what in the
world? How is it? Kelly Pavle, like the
list goes on and on. So, my dad is a
butcher and uh he used to sell meat to
Kelly Pavle. So, that's my Kelly Pavle
got all his meat from my dad. So, Oh,
there you go. I I want genetic tracing.
I want some answers out of that city.
You know what? It's the grit mentality,
right? Like, no, it's not, isn't it? No,
it's not. You are drugging kids. You're
you're genetically crispering them.
You're doing something. I don't care
what you say about I grew up in the
country. I grew up my graduating class
was like 70 kids, not 700. And we
probably had, I don't know, three or
four kids ever in my high school play
college football. Oh, yeah. I was like
the second probably the first or second
person to ever do it. Well, second or
third. You got you got 50 NFL players
every year at your school. Yeah. It's
unbelievable. Well, in the area, right?
you know like um because that's just
Youngsttown Boardman where I went
there's you know five other schools
Maurice Clarrett right there like Warren
Harding um Colonel Mooney also produced
phenomenal athletes um I mean that's
what I think you're taught early on
growing up there probably still now um
but back when I was in high school we
had the highest murder rate in the
country like people never believe me but
when I was a sophomore in high school.
We literally had the highest murder rate
in the country. And my mother like she
worked for welfare. So she was like in
the center of that on the east side of
Youngtown. Yeah. Um in this plaza she
worked in like that's where most of
these murders happened. Um so I think
you learned early on that like your
ticket out of I mean because really to
that area too. I mean what is considered
middle class in Youngsttown is consider
considered poverty everywhere else. So
like I, you know, in all honesty, like
grew up like lower middle class. Um, and
so you learn that your ticket out of
town is being good at sports. Like it,
yes, I love school. Um, and so that
helped, but at the end of the day, like
my goal in life was to be an astronaut
or an athlete, right? And I was able to
at one point accomplish that and be an
athlete, but that's all you think about
growing up there. It's like, well,
LeBron, too, right? Yeah. He's just that
that whole man, you know, sports is king
there. I get it. Well, I I uh when next
time when you tap in here from Mars or
wherever else you come in, I I want
answers about Youngstown. I'm not
letting you up for this. So, well, just
ask uh what's his name? Bruce
Springsteen since he has that song. Of
course. Yeah.
Um, thank you so much for coming out
here. I know it was a long trek and uh
really appreciate everything. There's
fascinating stuff and uh it's been a
long time. We've known each other for
many, many, many years. Oh my gosh.
Yeah. I mean, it's all through science,
right? And then we all went our separate
ways in academia and then outside of
academia and Yep. And it's always nice
to see another scientist who's a true
meatthead. Yeah, exactly. Oh, I I
embrace being a meatthead. Right. That's
my book. Thank you so much. Of course. I
hope you enjoyed that conversation today
with Dr. Allison Bger. If you want to
see more about Allison, read more of her
work, grab her book, or follow along
with any of her resources, please check
out the show notes for direct links.
Thank you for joining for today's
episode. My goal, as always, is to share
exciting scientific insights that help
you perform at your best. If the show
resonates with you and you want to help
ensure this information remains free and
accessible to anyone in the world, there
are a few ways that you can support.
First, you can subscribe to the show on
YouTube, Spotify, and Apple. And on
Apple, and Spotify, you can leave us up
to a five-star review. Subscribing and
leaving a review really does help us a
lot. Also, please check out our
sponsors. The show would not exist
without them, and their exceptional
products and services. Finally, you can
share today's episode with a friend who
you think would enjoy it. If you have
any content questions or suggestions,
please put those in the comment section
on YouTube. I really do try my best to
read them all and to see what you have
to say. I use my Instagram and
ex-profiles also exclusively for
scientific communication. So, those are
great places to follow along for more
learning. My handle is Dr. Andy Galpin
on both platforms. We also have an email
newsletter that distills all of our
episodes in the most actionable
takeaways. We have newsletters on how to
improve fitness in V2 max, how to build
muscle and strength, and much more. To
subscribe to the newsletter, just go to
performpodcast.com and click newsletter.
It's completely free and we do not share
your email with anybody. Thank you for
listening and never forget in the famous
words of Bill Bowererman, if you have a
body, you are an athlete.